[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
this is adam conrad for software
engineering radio
today we'll be talking with steven
skinner about technical job interview
preparation with data structures and
algorithms
steven skinner is a distinguished
teaching professor of computer science
at stony brook university
he serves as the director of the
institute for ai driven discovery
and innovation at stony brook his
research interests include algorithm
design data science and their
applications to biology
skeena is the author of several popular
books in the fields of algorithms
programming and data science the
algorithm design manual is widely used
as an undergraduate text in algorithms
and within the tech industry for job
interview preparation steve
thanks for coming on to software
engineering radio thank you very much
for having me
now normally we would start with the
definitions for our topic but for data
structures and algorithms
that's a bit too fundamental so if
you're looking for a definition
i would encourage you to check out a
source like wikipedia but for today's
topic i want to focus more on the why
why are data structures and algorithms
just so fundamentally important
to our understanding as professional
software developers
so i think of data structures and
algorithms as kind of being the primary
abstraction
behind computer programs data structures
are the
things we can do without thinking they
need to be
how do we and they're kind of the thing
that we organize algorithms around
in working on an algorithm you're
typically manipulating data
in one way or another and they have been
developed a lot of very clever data
structures
that enable you to do certain operations
very very quickly
and efficiently and it turns out to be
very natural to structure a lot of
algorithm design
problems around what data structures you
have access to
and what operations they do another way
you know when i when you posed this
question to me i started thinking about
it a little bit
and one thing that i think is that
algorithms and data structures are
really kind of what separate computer
scientists from coders
okay computer scientists have ways of
thinking about things
that are through an algorithmic lens and
i think that one of the importance of
learning
how algorithms work and how data
structures work
is basically to turn you into a real
computer scientist
and that's probably one of the reasons
it's so important in interview prep
what are some examples of data
structures and algorithms we use in
everyday work
that we may not realize we're using
so the simplest data structures that you
probably use in a uh
programming are arrays or matrices
you know if you grew up programming
matlab or fortran
probably these were the only kind of
data structures that you basically had
access to
arrays and matrices and they were good
for certain kinds of things they're
obviously good for certain kinds of
numerical computation
they're good for storing things although
they don't really give you
support for fast retrieval by
looking by content okay i guess one way
to think about an array array lets you
look up something when you know where it
is but if you want a fast way to try to
look up a particular element a
particular record
you start getting into more
sophisticated
data structures for for storing things
typically called dictionaries
and the kind of dictionaries you're
probably exposed to are things like hash
tables
um hash tables are very very practical
data structures for
storing keys so you can look them up
quickly
by content um and there's a host of
other
data structures things like binary
search trees
and priority queues and lots of
different things
so they're kind of a a certain number of
canonical data structures
that any you know reasonable algorithm
designer should know about
because they provide certain operations
to retrieve data quickly or to
manipulate data quickly
okay on a you know a reasonably large
data set
one thing that stands out to me is that
these fundamental data structures and
algorithms
may take a different form or a different
name than we're used to when we
see them in an academic setting so we
may call them arrays or length lists
but in javascript for example we do have
arrays but we also have
objects which represent hash tables or
dictionaries so it's interesting that
sort of
each language has its own way of
abstracting itself
these fundamental objects into things
that are
a part of the nomenclature for a given
language python is another example where
they make frequent use of dictionaries
well one thing that you're saying that i
think is interesting is to realize that
different programming languages
make a certain degree of algorithm more
visible or more transparent than others
so when you're programming in something
like c you are programming you know near
the
sort of near the bare metal and an array
is an array
and when you look something up it's
basically going to a memory location
that who's
whose position it can compute in
constant time and pulling the thing out
in languages like python for example
arrays
are implemented as hash tables these are
these more complicated
but more general probabilistic data
structures
that are able to retrieve items by
content
that are very very powerful and very
very general
and something every kind of programmer
should know about
another example i can think of would be
c so in c and c
plus plus the standard templating
library offers vectors but in
academic setting these would be
considered lists or linked lists
but in a language like that uh vectors
are essentially the names that represent
uh these kinds of fundamental objects so
i think in summary what we're really
thinking about here is
ensuring that there are fundamental
structures and they just may be
part of a different name depending on
the context of the language that you are
using
right so i guess in a lot of people my
students always tell me who attend the
program in java talk about hash maps
and these are kind of obviously i guess
by the name people get the idea they are
hash tables underlooking it
but but there's a level of abstraction
that that when you're using a
pre-implemented
data structure an abstract data type
you don't really know you know what the
operations are you know what the
definitions of what you can do
on them and the operations you can do on
them but you don't really know how
they're actually
implemented and one of the things that's
interesting is for a given set of
operations like the main operations on a
dictionary
things like inserting items and looking
them up by content
and deleting items there are many
different ways you can
implement this data structure
where the performance of certain
operations is better than the
performance of certain other operations
and that um understanding that
difference
is important to getting good performance
on a lot of applications
can you give us an example of an
algorithm we might want to write on our
own
so if you wanted to for example search
through
items in sorted order you started
hinting about the idea of sorting as
kind of a fundamental algorithm problem
if you want to a a common operation
is you would like to take elements that
maybe
you know that you're working with and
retrieve them one by one in kind of a
assorted order
so let's say that you were maintaining a
a queue of jobs
you might want to process the jobs in
order from highest priority to lowest
priority
and um you know either do the most
important jobs before you do the
the less important ones or do the ones
that hadn't been looked at for a while
before you do the ones that had gotten
attention recently
if you have kind of a priority score
associated with each item
you might want to be able to insert new
items you might want to be able to
change the priority
of an existing item you might want to
delete an item
because it's no longer something you
care about or
you might want to find say get me the
next most
important item and being able to search
through something like that
a hash table which is normally a great
data structure
would be very bad at that because it
doesn't maintain a sense of order among
things a sorted array maintains an order
of things
a binary search tree maintains an order
something called the priority queue
maintains an order of things
but so hash tables are great if you're
looking things up by name
and you want to get you know get items
by name
if you want to store me and tell me what
is the next most important thing or the
next thing in alphabetical order
hash tables would be a bad idea
yeah and this makes sense because for
some languages like javascript they
don't have a concept of a priority queue
but for other languages like c
you have something available in the
standard library to access
right so if you know in certain
languages there may be something like a
standard template library
which will have things like priority
queues in them
and so if you are using a language that
has a good library
of abstract data types it's important to
kind of know
what each one of these is good for and
that's one of the reasons to take an
algorithms course or to study
algorithms is because knowing why a
priority queue
is a useful thing and where it is where
it comes in
enables you to use first of all if you
have a fast implementation then you know
why you would use it and it gives you an
abstraction to think about when you
think around when you're trying to
design an algorithm
a lot of my students before they take an
algorithms class
they say well everything is a container
and they kind of are used to just saying
well i'll go
through all my data and i'll look at it
maybe one by one
realizing that there's these richer
abstractions available
gives you a lot of power when it comes
to thinking about data
there was a quote i once read that said
that civilization advances
based on the number of things we can do
without thinking
once you understand the kind of basic
abstract data types
and what they're good for you can think
at the level of these data types
rather than low-level things like loops
and
arrays
so what you're really saying then is
that it's so much more important to
truly understand
intuitively what we're working with
because anyone can really
handle the implementation pieces of the
algorithms or the data structures
but when you are able to intuit the use
cases for them
you now can start to think about a whole
set of problems to solve
so with the priority queue example we
don't have to think about
how does a priority queue actually get
constructed or how do i think about
the insert and pop instead i think about
priorities okay i have a list of items i
have to think about the priority
i now understand how a priority queue
works under the hood
and so for me it's now about thinking
about
the applications of those things now
that i understand really what's going on
underneath and why i would use these
algorithms
and not just the what or the how
right and that's one of the reasons why
in in
a lot of these data structures to
implement them to the point where you
you know they're
they're usable is a little challenged
but not insurmountable and you know in
my book i
include implementations of you know
important data structures like stacks
and queues and uh
priority queues and uh all kinds of
things because i think that it's
important to understand how these things
work under the hood
so if i'm studying for interviews
there's so much to cover
what one area in particular do you think
requires the most study
when prepping for interviews
well i think that learning probably the
single
data structure that people need to know
most about
is probably hashing that uh i once heard
a lecture from a guy who was eventually
became the vice president
of search at google and he said that the
three most important algorithms at
google
were hashing hashing and hashing and um
hashing is useful as a technique for
building
a you know a a dictionary structure
so you can look things up you know you
can insert items and you can look up and
get them
but hashing is a very very powerful
uh technique and idea for doing lots of
other kinds of things
so maybe an example of this would be uh
how does google know that a
when google has its crawler walking over
the web
when it fetches a document how does it
know that it hasn't seen this document
before
you know you could think my god if
google really wants to know if this
document's ever seen before
it's got to compare it against
everything on the web
and that would be you know order the
size of the web
but what if let's say you compute a hash
code
on a document a hashcode is kind of a
numerical
quantity that is designed to be
deterministic for a a particular file
in other words for any time you see this
file you're going to get the same number
out of it
it's like in a unique identifier but you
can use a hash function to construct an
identifier that
is long enough that it's unlikely
if this document had not previously seen
been seen by on your searches that some
other document will have the same
identifier
so it's long enough to be pretty unique
but
short enough to be quick to work with
and for doing things like identifying
duplicate documents
um if you're trying to build a
plagiarism detector
to try to figure out you know my
students look my student
ambitious students might be trying to
copy a homework from somewhere
on the web how will i know whether or
not
part of their document okay was in fact
stolen from a web page
well if you hash windows of the text you
get these unique codes
you can see whether or not this code has
existed anywhere else
in previously submitted assignments or
or the web or something like that and
that you know
that that can give you a way to find
these identifiers so
hashing is a very useful thing in many
different ways
we think of it as a as a data structure
thing
but there's a lot it's more than just
building a hash table
hashing is an idea you know um
again we'll talk about my book i guess
at some point but um
as i've revised my book for a new
edition
one of the things i did was emphasize
hashing in this latest revision because
i think it's something that's really
important
that's kind of only grown important and
important so in recent years
you talking about hashing actually
reminds me about text compression i know
that in text compression
what they are trying to do is take a lot
of data and pull it down into very small
pieces so right like in that sense
you're using hashing to take
long strings of text and to bring them
down into much smaller pieces
actually it's a little a little
different there i would say because
there's somewhat different
um goals when you compress your document
the one thing you care about is that
when you uncompress it
if it's a text document when you
compress a document
it's important yes you want to compress
it so it's smaller
but you absolutely want to make sure
that when you reconstruct it
you can reconstruct the entire document
from the compressed version
that's certainly true when you're doing
a uh
you know any kind of text compression
you'd be
upset if you compress your your you know
research paper
and it came back garbled so the the key
with a hash code is that you can find a
very very small representation
that is unique it's not enough
information to reconstruct
the whole document from it but it's
enough that it's sort of unique
and so you can tell whether you've seen
it before so you know typically for
example i guess if you use a typical
text compression algorithm
maybe you can shrink the document to
30 of its original size when you use a
hash code you could take
any document you know maybe you know a
megabyte long or even longer
and produce a 128-bit code or a 256-bit
code
that would be fairly unique to that
document right so in that sense we're
actually taking what would be like the
title
and abstracting out the entire document
into this one sort of unique identifier
right it gives me a way to recognize
whether i've seen it before
without actually reconstructing it
okay so um maybe maybe as a metaphor you
might imagine something like
you found the most unique phrase in the
document
okay if i only stored that if i saw this
you know this phrase i would recognize
i've seen this document before
okay but of course you couldn't
reconstruct the rest of it
that makes sense switching things over
to algorithms so we've covered the
fundamental data structures we should
really be thinking about and
we've seen some of the ones that we may
not realize we've already been using for
a really long time
but switching over to algorithms that
one takes the most focus for people in
interview prep
especially graphs and trees i find when
people are studying for algorithm exams
for uh tech interview prep the focus so
much is on
graphs and trees traversing them
navigating them
finding ways of sorting items within
graphs and trees
it's such a fundamental piece of what
we're doing in
in tech prep i think i remember seeing
from facebook once that they said if you
really focused on graphs
you would get the most bang for your
buck there same with trees so we'd love
to learn more about
understanding fundamental algorithms as
well okay
before i even get into algorithms i want
to make sure that the idea of a graph or
a network is clear to
who's listening here because um a lot of
different kinds of
uh data in the world an astonishingly
wide variety of data in the world
really can be kind of represented as
networks of
nodes okay or vertices
pairs of which are connected by edges
that's what a network is
and so the road network um
you know uh what what what intersections
are there in the world
and which pairs of intersections are
connected by roads
that would define a graph and obviously
there's
there's shortest there's problems that
are on road networks that are quite
natural
like finding the shortest path between
places
when you use your gps
it's kind of amazing you can say find me
the shortest path from here
to some obscure place you know all the
way across the country
and for free in you know in in a
fraction of a second
you know your google or whatever your
map system is
is going to tell you the absolute
shortest path in this network
in order to do that there's got to be a
fast algorithm there's very interesting
fast algorithms
like dijkstra's algorithm that finds the
shortest path between any two places in
a network
that's obviously a useful thing for
understanding
roads but what's interesting about
graphs or graph problems
is that there's a small number of
algorithm problems
that are relatively common that tend to
appear
in a lot of different settings and so
the thing that's useful for interview
prep
is to know the the basic graph problems
things like shortest path
things like finding minimum spanning
tree things
like how do you do with traversals of
graphs to walk over the network
these are things like breadth first
search and depth first search
and understanding these things gives you
a lot of power
for solving a lot of different problems
and we can reference
these data structures and these
algorithms all within your book the
algorithm design manual
so switching gears uh steve yeggy a very
famous
blogger and ex-googler once referred to
your book as the book that helped me
understand just how astonishingly
commonplace and important graph problems
are
it has since become canon as one of the
top books to study when preparing for
job interviews so my first question for
you then
is why do you think this book is so
heavily cited for job interview prep and
what is people's allure to it
first of all it has been you know i'm
i'm very gratified
by the number of people who have used
the uh
the book and uh i i get letters from
people quite often
to say you got me your job at my job at
google you know i read your book and i
didn't know the algorithm stuff and then
i read your book and i was able to
squeak by my interview
and so i'm always very excited when i
get people who say these things
what i think makes my book useful for
interview prep
is is a couple things one is it is i
think
more accessible than most other
algorithm
books algorithms is an area that is
traditionally a part of theoretical
computer science
and it's an area that involves
a lot of mathematical analysis it's an
area
that involves a lot of reasoning and
formal reasoning
and proofs of correctness and proofs of
efficiency and
many of the the standard texts in
algorithms
kind of are approaching it as here is a
famous algorithm i want to make sure you
understand it at a level that you can
you can
prove its efficiency and prove its
correctness
and i think it's easy to lose sight of
the forest for the trees what my book
tries to do is to stress the
intuitions behind algorithm design you
know how is it that you should think
about these things
what should you know when you learn
about sorting algorithms the average
person learns about a lot of sorting
algorithms and they learn about
analyses of these and all but the
question of why are there different
algorithms what are really the lessons
you should take away from it
when you learn about something like
quicksort which is a famous sorting
algorithm
it's not so much that you know ethan you
know it's good to know how it what you
know
exactly how it works and stuff like that
but it's kind of this representative
of using randomization in algorithms
and understanding why it should work
well
with high probability even though
there's a terrible worst case
that's an intuition thing and uh maybe
you could see it by a big
formal analysis but i think my book
gives it gives a lot of intuition i find
that
you know it's very easy to get lost in
the intricacies
of algorithm analysis and so that's why
when i write my book i really want to
leave it at the intuition level
and i think people find it a lot more
accessible
i hear some people who say that oh i
tried to study
uh one of the the uh you know really
detailed algorithm book something like
the corman
book which is very famous out of mit
that's a great book
but you have to kind of understand some
things in order to really appreciate it
and i think that going through my book
people can get get an intuition for
things
and that's kind of what i what i what i
try to teach i really try to teach an
intuition and i think that that that
pays off rather than
rather than being excessively formal
about about things
i really want people to understand
what's important and why
so that's one reason why it's used for
interview prep another thing is that i
do include
implementations for many of the the the
primary algorithms
so people do get a chance to look at uh
some code
and when they look at some code they you
know they
some people think better about things
when they see code and certainly it adds
for some level of concreteness
so i think that the combination of the
intuition
of ideas which is what i write about and
seeing the concrete implementation
resonates with people it resonated with
me i took your class online
audited it as well as studied the book
so
for people that are actually taking the
class
or reading the book for interview prep
do you think any independent learners
who are doing interview prep need to do
anything differently than your students
are doing when they're taking the course
themselves
so when people use the book for
interview prep there's kind of two
different
aspects of uh interview prep where i'll
but in the course of interviews
algorithms knowledge tends to come out
in two different ways
one thing is that that many companies
do screenings things like by companies
like hacker rank
they have coding contests coding tests
that they make people
do before they to screen them before
they even give them an interview
and quite often these programming tests
are about algorithmic kinds of problems
so one aspect of being a
you know let's say getting through the
the interview process
is making sure you pass your basic
algorithmic
coding thing and part of that is looking
at code
and playing around and implementing some
of the classical algorithms
i hear peop some people basically at
least if they don't at least they study
the implementations
in my book but but usually people want
to
you know do some programming with them
to make sure they get a hang of it
so part of it is fluency with
programming
and the other part is the whiteboard
preparation
in you know if you go to an interview at
companies usually
they will at some point ask you an
algorithm design
problem at a whiteboard and they want to
hear how you think they want to hear how
you approach it
they want to hear what questions you
want to ask you know to
to make sure you understand the problem
and so these are kind of
two different two different skills to
learn when i teach my algorithms course
again it's you know at the end of stony
brook university
we i i don't
make them re-implement classic
algorithms
because i think that uh it's more on the
conceptual idea
so they don't get experience at doing
the you know some of the
kind of contest level programming that
these programming contest puzzle type
programming so for that actually it's
it's funny i
i have another book which i wrote called
programming challenges which was
designed to
teach people how to do puzzle problems
for programming contests
and i think this is something that uh is
part of the
process of studying for an interview
but the deeper and more meaningful part
i think is
is being able to go to a white board and
know how to think about algorithms
and um for doing that i think that
reading through the algorithm book you
know in the order that it's been
skip the stuff that you know about
although don't be too quick to skip the
introductory chapters which are on data
structures
because if you don't understand the
basic data structures you'll eventually
kind of
we kind of assume that that you kind of
have mastered that
and you'll eventually kind of fade out
if you uh
you know don't have the basics down but
i think that learning how to solve
problem b you know work at a white board
involves
solving algorithm design problems and
those are the kind of things i do assign
my students for homework and that's the
kind of thing that i have plenty of
these kind of problems in my book to
give people practice at solving these
kind of problems
and that raises such a good point
because for many people they look at
these books and they think well
how is this going to help me if i have
to implement breadth first search
you know i could do that and i can go
through every single step
in the pseudo code but that's not really
getting me anywhere but what matters
is the underpinnings of what breadth
first search represents
so if i know that i have to say do
something like shortest path i know that
i have to think about in my head
going from one place to the next and i
have to explore
all those opportunities in order to get
there so i think you raise a really good
point that it just
isn't going to cut it if you're just
going to memorize things without really
retaining
and understanding and intuiting exactly
what goes into
these algorithm designs if you can get
there
then you're so much further along
because now you're adapting to patterns
you're understanding
the underlying question that's really
being asked and you can apply
these algorithms through that kind of
analysis when you're
tackling these kinds of problems right
right and and
there also are a lot of
kind of problems that are what i'll say
using the same general techniques
but the words differ and so if you don't
know and
and and you know the details differ and
so so like for example there's an
algorithm design technique called
dynamic programming
that is a uh you know it's it's a
technique for designing algorithms that
once you understand it
okay is actually relatively easy to
apply
but until you understand that it's like
magic you know so one of the things you
have to do is you need to see enough
examples you need to try to understand
you know of different
seemingly wildly different problems all
of which kind of turn out to be the same
technique
and i think that that's the kind of
thing you can get from
a you know book on a you know algorithms
is a is a very very interesting
and well-developed algorithm design very
interesting and well-developed subject
and i think that you can get that from a
you know essentially a course on
algorithm design
in ways that i don't think you can get
so easily
by just solving a couple of puzzle
problems there's a certain
you have to kind of go through the
thinking problems and those are the
kinds of things that uh
you know we do in the book i think a
really important thing to also emphasize
is that
for many people doing just the problems
in the book
isn't going to cut it i know for example
when i took an algorithms course when i
took your course
and audited it it was really difficult
for me to understand dynamic programming
for example
so i had to read through all the
examples in the book multiple times
i still didn't get it and you know you
pointed this out earlier that
you basically have to see the example
enough times in order for you to have it
click
i mean for me i had to go to wikipedia i
had to watch a couple of youtube videos
for it to really stick so i think just
for people out there who are doing tech
interview prep
it's not going to be sufficient to say
okay i'm just going to go through these
five problems that were assigned for
this chapter
and if i do that then i'll know
everything there is to know about
dynamic programming
uh that's just not gonna cut it you have
to really be able to have the honesty
with yourself to say
okay i am going to study this until i
actually understand fundamentally what
is going on and that may take
more or maybe even less than what is
regarded in the book i think you
mentioned this earlier that
if you're going to do something and
you're going to skip the fundamental
pieces of the data structures
that you might want to make sure you
really know it but you can gloss over it
if you really know those areas really
well
so for things like yeah like dynamic
programming just make sure that you
really understand it
and give yourself permission to do more
problems so that you can really
understand it and don't shut yourself
short
right so i mean that you know algorithm
design is really about
a certain number of ideas and techniques
you know it's not an unbelievably long
list of
ideas and techniques but they are a
little bit deep to
understand and they're a little tricky
to understand to get a sense as to when
a divide and conquer kind of algorithm
one where good things happen if you
split the problem into smaller pieces
that are of the same type
solve them and then put them the answers
back together
something like a divide and conquer not
knowing when a binary search
type of strategy is an interesting thing
to do
you know often people will not tell you
implement the binary search
they will tell you maybe tell me how i
can implement something to find a square
root
an approximation of the square root of a
number
and you know you could do that i guess
if i guess maybe if you remember your uh
your math well enough you may remember
something about taylor series or god
knows what
but if you don't if you think in terms
of binary search you can get this idea
of honing in on an answer
you try a number and you square it okay
and if it's bigger than what you're
trying to find the square root of
well that tells you something about a
number that's too big to be the square
root and if you try a smaller number and
when you square it it's less than your
target
then that number is too small to be your
square root
and by doing kind of a search like this
a binary search
you can hone in on your answer and
i guess that's again that's a specific
kind of a problem
but there are relatively small number of
techniques that if you really kind of
understand it
you can solve lots and lots of different
algorithm problems
and i think that you know about an
introductory algorithm class or a book
like mine
is enough to really kind of get what
these basic techniques are
so in addition to actually creating the
algorithms we also have to analyze them
and one way we talk about that
is with big o notation and that's a huge
thing that comes up in interview prep
so what does the o stand for in big o
and what exactly are we looking for here
when we're thinking about
analyzing an algorithm to figure out its
efficiency
the big o is one of the things that
myogram students dread
unnecessarily it's something that looks
a little mathy looks a little scary
but big o to my mind stands to sort of
like on the order of things
so one of the things that makes
algorithm design
and analysis a a good and enduring
subject
is that you can kind of analyze
algorithms in a
computer-independent way you're trying
to understand this
the running time that an algorithm is
going to take in terms of the size of
the input
it makes sense that the sort if i ask
you how you know what is the
the running time of quick sort
the answer shouldn't be 10 seconds it
should depend
on how many elements you're actually
sorting
if you're sorting a few elements it's
obviously going to be faster than when
you're sorting a large number of
elements
but we're interested in how is the
running time grow
as a function of the size of the problem
you give it
so typically we are given a what you
call we'll say that we have n
elements of the input and we want to
know
something about what is the rough
running time as a function of
n and um this notion of rough running
time
can be kind of made precise through this
notation that they call the big o
notation
we don't care if we're off by a factor
of 2 or
10 or 100 but we do want to know how it
depends on
n which is the size of the problem
so some algorithms look at the data once
or twice or a hundred times and each
element once or twice or a hundred times
if you have n items that will take order
end time sometimes you look at all pairs
of things
and there's n squared pairs and so that
would be something that is
order n squared and some of these fancy
algorithms and data structures have
running times that are
proportional to something like n times
the logarithm of n
so there's a little bit of math involved
in knowing what logarithms are
and where they that they arise why they
come up
and you know but but this this big o
notation
gives you a way to talk about how fast
an algorithm is
in a kind of machine independent way
this is one of the reasons why it's good
to learn algorithms because
it is machine independent it's something
that will stick with you
the you know the stuff that i learned
about algorithms 30 years ago
every bit of it is still true and uh
still
still useful and one of the reasons is
because we
are not talking about running times in
terms of seconds
but running at times in terms of the big
o one example that really
makes sense to me is around fibonacci
sequence so that's a really common one
when we start talking about recursion or
even dynamic programming
really small numbers for fibonacci you
can answer them instantly
but for even normal numbers like 50 or
100 something that you can conceptualize
even these small numbers if you run them
with fibonacci on a naive algorithm
it won't be able to run on your machine
it will just heat up and it won't be
able to finish in time
so that's sort of how i see this
applying for folks in the real world is
you have to understand the algorithmic
complexity
because if you can't do something in a
short amount of time
very quickly for exponential algorithms
things can get out of hand
but if you have a good algorithm for
this and you can analyze something that
is much more efficient
you know for example with dynamic
programming you can do fibonacci
in a very optimized way so that it can
run in linear time
so you know choosing the right algorithm
can really be important recognizing the
difference between
polynomial algorithms time algorithms
things that are
order n or order n squared
and things that are exponential like
order 2 to the n
or n factorial is you know one of the
the most fundamental things in algorithm
design
and that often recursive algorithms
left of their own devices turn out to be
exponential time algorithms and
whenever anything is exponential it
grows
obviously rapidly but you don't see it
growing rapidly until it hits a point
and in fact this covid
epidemic that we've been living through
is a good example of this
the number of people infected by the
virus
unchecked by preventive you know
preventive measures
would grow exponentially and what
happened was
it was doubling let's say every week
and doubling from one to two patients
nobody saw it
two to four patients nobody saw it but
when suddenly you went from 1 million to
2 million
and then 4 million and 16 million
suddenly
it becomes very visible and when you
look at exponential time algorithms
it's the same kind of thing you know i
one thing i do in my class is i have
students
implement an exponential time algorithm
and i have a contest for the fastest
implementation
where they have to be clever to try to
keep the exponential growth at bay as
much as possible
but everybody starts being very very
happy because they run it on the small
input files and it's almost instant
and then they go to the next largest
size and suddenly they hit a wall
and it you know instead of taking
seconds it will take hours
and learning to recognize when you have
an algorithm
that is exponential time is a
fundamental thing in
algorithm design sometimes it's okay
because you know there are there's
techniques like backtracking
and pruning and branching bound these
are sort of search techniques that kind
of
can sometimes push that exponential
stuff
push it down enough that you can still
solve interesting problems on it
but then there are other algorithm
design techniques like you mentioned alg
dynamic programming that can turn what
would have been an exponential time
recursive algorithm into a pussycat that
will run in
linear time or maybe n squared time
and again being able to see these things
requires understanding
you know first of all what's the
difference between exponential and
polynomial and so recognizing when
you've got something that's going to be
slow for large n
and learning a couple of techniques that
may give you a chance to beat that down
okay so i'm convinced i'm a developer i
just lost my job
and i know i need to study for data
structures and algorithms to
get a good job at a great prestigious
company how should i read your book
is there an order i should change based
on the class or
how the book is written is there
anything that i should do
because i'm a job seeker instead of a
student to best prepare for tech
interview prep using your course
materials and your book
first of course how much you should read
depends upon
how much time you have and how much time
you devote to it
obviously i think that you know if you
read the whole thing you will know more
than if you read a part of it
but again there's two different i
organized the book in these two halves
kind of
because i think that there is a
distinction between the basic techniques
that you really kind of need to know
to design um you know
basically to design basic algorithms
okay that's the stuff in the first half
and so that stuff i think is like bread
and butter
the other stuff is it's true that
there are a certain number of
algorithm problems that arise all the
time in practice
you guys may have heard of the traveling
salesman problem we talked about
finding the shortest path uh there's
problems in geometry maybe the first
thing that happens when you deal with
points you might be interested
in something like finding something
called the convex hull
so there's a certain number of
specialized algorithm problems
that are not elementary they're good
things to know
and it's they're good things to
recognize when you see them
and so the second half of my book is
kind of i call it the hitchhiker's guide
to algorithms it's kind of
a catalog of what do i think are the
most
important kinds of algorithm problems
that tend to come up and that people
you know algorithm researchers have
figured out what is the right way to
think about these kind of problems
so the second part is kind of like for
every one of these problems i give you
kind of an executive summary
of what what you should do if you have
this problem
if you have a traveling salesman problem
what should you be concerned with how
should you deal with it
and i think that it's very good for
people to browse through the back of the
catalog
at least if you can get an idea of what
these
problems are and keep them in your head
what is a set cover problem what is a
traveling salesman
problem what is a knapsack problem
when you see these kind of things in
practice
you can you know kind of take advantage
of that knowledge
and say wait a second if i know that
this is a set cover problem
and i know skeena's book had four pages
about what you should do if you have set
cover problems
just recognizing what the problem is and
then referring
to this for reference gives you power
and so
i think that it's important if you're
doing an interview prep you should
probably
i think you should try to master as much
as you can of the first half of the book
and i think you should try to browse
through the catalog i
i try to have pictures of each problem
so that you can kind of get an intuition
about what
is actually going on with it and a lot
of people find the pictures useful for
kind of pinpointing what the challenge
they face is really called
because a lot of problems if you know
the name of it you can look something up
but if you don't know that a knapsack
problem is a knapsack problem
you're not gonna find the algorithm by
googling it
and uh i think that so i think the
catalog is fun to browse through i think
people
people like looking at the pictures and
uh if they're
there's when they find the one that they
really care about
i think that it quickly gets them going
in the direction that is most useful for
their application
so we know the structure of the book but
just as important as
reading the book is practicing the
problems within the book
now if i'm an independent studier who is
trying to study for interview prep
how do i know if i got them right are
there any places i can go online where i
can figure out the solutions to the
problems that you have in your book
so i have a website with the book
www.algorist.com
dot-com but so part of it is i keep an
online solution wiki there so people who
have
had these problems uh have tried to work
out solutions and
you know if people want to go there
that's a good way to get some kind of a
solution
one hint that i would recommend for
people that maybe isn't obvious
is that it is good to work out algorithm
design
problems with somebody else if you have
a buddy
who is interested in learning this at
the same time you are
i think it is a great thing if the two
people if you can sit together
and argue with a blackboard what is the
right way to do these things
because one of the hallmarks about
algorithm design
problems is there is a flesh of an idea
that once you have it defines the
solution
but until you see the flash of the idea
you're kind of muddling around
and you know getting two people and
talking together
one guy poses has an idea the other guy
says why it's wrong
i find that it's uh i i like to work
things out
with somebody else when i'm doing
algorithm design and research
i definitely like to have somebody else
at the blackboard with me
and we generate much better ideas
arguing back and forth
and uh i think that the same thing is
true with with with prep if you can find
a buddy
this is a good thing if you need
solutions i think that uh
the website the the solution wiki at
algorist.com
is a good one algorith by the way is an
old english word
for someone who's skilled in problem
solving
and uh numerical reckoning and so that's
why i kind of chose that as our uh
our website and that's great to hear so
if i'm
able to study for this i can actually go
to the algorithm and check out the
answers to the problem so i know i'm
headed in the right direction now for
some people to play devil's advocates
they fundamentally don't even want to
take these kinds of questions because
they
think that i shouldn't have to be asked
data structures and algorithms questions
in interviews and many people think that
the whole process
is fundamentally broken on how we hire
what is your take on the heavy focus on
data structures and algorithms questions
in the industry
okay so first of all i think algorithms
and and data structures are an
incredibly beautiful and useful subject
and i think of them as what
distinguishes
a computer scientist from a coder this
much i think
is true that said i
i'll admit that i am you know i'm not
sure
that the emphasis on algorithm design
okay
as a test thing to screen out good
software engineers from bad software
engineers
is necessarily the best way to do it
we had a startup for a while named
general sentiment and we used to hire
engineers
and um all the engineers that we we
were interviewing with us they knew they
were going to be speaking to me they all
knew about my book
they figured i was going to grill them
on algorithm design
the honest-to-god truth is i never asked
any of them any algorithm design
problems because i was uh the company
needed people who were building big
distributed systems
and i needed to know sort of the
sophistication of the kind of thing they
could build
and you know in the course of
discussions what was your biggest
program you ever wrote what did it do
you can get an idea of whether people
are you know have have worked with
things with a certain level of
complexity
and what kind of things they like to do
so i do think that algorithm design
is a very important thing i think as a
professor
i can usually tell you know who's good
or bad at that kind of thing based on
the grade in their algorithms class
so i don't think that you know people
usually can't sneak through an
algorithms class
with get a good grade if they really
don't know what they're doing
but it it provides a way that people
think so i guess the
the rationale here is that it provides a
way to understand how people's thought
process is
and sometimes you you know what you know
that's i think a critical thing to tell
when you're interviewing somebody
how do they reason about things you know
can they do deep
you know do a certain level of thinking
and clear-headedness
and i guess on that level i think
algorithm design is a good way to test
that
now i noticed on your publisher's
website you have a new version of this
book coming out
which hasn't been updated since the
second edition way way back in 2008
so there's a lot to update in 12 years
what has changed in the upcoming version
of the algorithm design manual
right well first of all i just wanted to
say this is as far as i'm concerned the
first official announcement
of the third edition i'm i'm always
reluctant to talk about a book until it
is
completely completely done um at this
point if i got hit by a car
the book is at the publisher and so i
can guarantee you there will be a third
edition out uh probably by the time
people listen to this so what's changed
in algorithm design so one of the great
things about algorithm design
is that it is a very foundational
classical thing
and so things don't change at the speed
of light
but they're you know when you look at it
over the last 10 years
there are a lot of things that have
changed one thing that has changed
is randomized algorithms
the idea of using random numbers to
design efficient algorithms
is something that has grown in
in power and in how widely it's used
so randomization is one thing that's new
i knew i have a
full chapter on randomized algorithms
which i wouldn't have had before
hashing is actually an example of a
randomized algorithm so
hashing is uh at least in the way that
you analyze it and you think about
it there's a connection between hashing
and randomization that's kind of
important so that's one thing that's new
another thing that's new is i added a
real chapter on divide and conquer
so um you know i had it in bits and
pieces but i
i give a much more thorough treatment of
that because that's something else also
that's become more important as you have
parallel computers one of the things
that you would like to do with a
parallel computer
is to take a job and break it into
smaller jobs
so that each processor can do something
different
and that's the kind of thing that divide
and conquer is very good about if you're
going to be thinking about parallel
computing
that's one of the things that's
important the other thing that
i have added was a new chapter on
dealing with np complete problems
we were talking earlier about
exponential time algorithms versus
polynomial time algorithms there's a
class of problems
called np complete problems that have
the property that
there is no algorithm possible for this
problem
you know for some weasel words for what
i mean by possible
but essentially once you can prove that
a problem or show that a problem is
np-complete
it means that there's not going to be
any algorithm that runs
in a polynomial time for it you're
doomed to an exponential algorithm
if you want the exact answer but there
are these cl techniques for trying to
come up with
approximate answers heuristic answers
that are important to understand and so
i've added a chapter
about these heuristic techniques things
like simulated annealing and stuff like
that
about ways to argue that your algorithm
is
uh come up with a heuristic and argue
that it will never do that badly
won't give you always give you the right
answer but it'll always come close
and finally i uh there's a lot of stuff
in the news about quantum
computing and so i give a very quick
introduction to quantum computing
but i think that someone can read this
and there's eight or ten pages there
and without going into the all the the
horrible physics and complex numbers and
all the yada yada
i think that it gives a pretty simple
idea
as to what the magic is with quantum
computing and why that why it's so
exciting
so these are the main things that i do i
have a lot more problems
and my presentation i think is a lot
better one thing i did was
we turned all the pictures and diagrams
in the book
into color so now one thing that's
changed since uh the last edition is
color printing is now a fairly routine
thing for
for book publishers and um
it's amazing how much clearer ideas are
when the drawings are kind of
represented in color and you think a
little bit about what the color can show
in order to you know kind of what is the
idea you want to convey and make that
concept pop
so i think that you know it's it's it's
easier to understand the picture with
you know
what's going on with the new figures and
the new presentation
and so i hope that people will be able
to read it and understand things even
better than with the previous editions
steve this is all great thank you so
much any final words for those preparing
for their next job
what about the interviewers who are
running these questions for folks
so first of all i encourage you know
obviously interviewing is a stressful
thing
do the best you can and it will probably
work i mean there is a reason why the
unemployment rate for software engineers
is low
it's because your skills are in demand
and i'm sure that you're going to be
able to get a good job
one thing i will tell you about the
interviewers and algorithm questions
that i have found
you know my my students all go off to
these interviews they come back and they
they they tell me about their interview
problems
and occasionally they come back and said
you know there was this algorithm
this question that this guy asked and uh
you know i gave him an answer and he
said no no no this is the answer
and that didn't make sense to me and
it's amazing to me how often the
interviewers
are wrong in the questions that they ask
um either that they
ask the question in a way that it's not
as precise as they would like
or their understanding of the answer is
actually
not as good as they should be you know
the reason
why they are interviewing you is that
they are a software engineer
at a company not that they are a real
algorithm expert
so sometimes recognize that your
interviewer is fallible
but again i think it's learning about
algorithm design
is a incredibly useful skill and it's
broadening and
you know there there are algorithms in
daily life that you kind of
see once you have a background in
you know in thinking this way and i you
know i
i wish you all good luck on your
interviews i
hope my book can help you guys learn
algorithms and come to appreciate it
better
and um it's something good to know and
uh i hope you i hope you guys can take
advantage of it
steve thank you so much for coming on
software engineering radio thank you
very much for having me this was a lot
of fun
this is adam conrad for software
engineering radio
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening